# Patrick Landon Ferree

Medical Museion, Fredericiagade 18, Copenhagen K, Denmark • patrick.ferree@sund.ku.dk • +45 93 86 71 37

## **PROFILE**

Patrick is a philosopher of science interested in epistemology, methodology, history, and social studies of the biomedical sciences. He has degrees in philosophy, chemistry, and biology, postdoc experience in exposure science, and is pursuing a PhD in science studies. His thesis project uses qualitative methods to investigate social and epistemic roles of shared research facilities, including core facilities and technology platforms.

#### EDUCATION

#### University of Copenhagen

Copenhagen, DK

PhD Student in Science Studies - Program in Medicine, Culture, and Society

in Progress

- Tentative Project: Reorganizing biomedical research: Shared research facilities and the process of discovery
- Advisors: Karin Tybjerg & Sara Green

### Duke University School of Medicine

Durham, NC, USA

PhD in Developmental Biology - Certificate in Cell and Molecular Biology

Apr 2022

- Dissertation: Temporal regulation of cell divisions in the embryo of Drosophila melanogaster
- Committee: Stefano Di Talia, Michel Bagnat, Danny Lew, Bernard Mathey-Prevot, Nick Buchler

#### University of California, San Diego

La Jolla, CA, USA

BA in Philosophy, BS in Chemistry, Minor in Political Science, magna cum laude

Jun 2012

## EXPERIENCE

#### University of Copenhagen

Copenhagen, DK Mar 2024 - Present

PhD Student, Advisors: Karin Tybjerg & Sara Green

• Affiliation: Medical Museion, Department of Public Health

- Affiliation: Novo Nordisk Foundation Center for Basic Metabolic Research (CBMR)
- Member: Center for Medical Science and Technology Studies (MeST)
- Guest: Section for History and Philosophy of Science, Department of Science Education
- Research: The social and epistemic roles of technology platforms in the biomedical sciences

#### The National Research Centre for the Working Environment

Copenhagen, DK

Postdoctoral Researcher, Advisor: Keld Alstrup Jensen

• Research: Occupational exposure to airborne particles

Jun 2022 - Mar 2024

#### Copenhagen Institute for Futures Studies

Intern, Advisor: Bogi Eliasen

Copenhagen, DK Jan - Jun 2022

• Research: Futures of healthcare and biomedicine

#### **Duke University School of Medicine**

PhD Student, Advisor: Stefano Di Talia

Durham, NC, USA Sep 2014 - Apr 2022

• Affiliation: Department of Cell Biology

• Research: Temporal patterning of mitosis in fly embryos

#### University of Texas, El Paso

Research Technician, Advisor: Laura O'Dell

El Paso, TX, USA Jan 2013 - Sep 2014

• Affiliation: Department of Psychology

• Research: Neuroscience of drug addiction in rats

## La Jolla, CA, USA

## Scripps Institute of Oceanography

Research Assistant, Advisor: Lynn Russell

Jan - Sep 2012

Research: Chemistry and physics of atmospheric aerosols

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- P. L. Ferree, M. Polat, J. K. Nøjgaard, K. A. Jensen, "Airborne particulate matter and diesel engine exhaust on infrastructure construction sites in the Copenhagen metropolitan area", *Annals of Work Exposures and Health*, Aug. 2024, doi.org/10.1093/annweh/wxae062 (Article).
- P. L. Ferree, M. Xing, J.Q. Zhang, S. Di Talia, "Structure-function analysis of Cdc25 Twine degradation at the Drosophila maternal-to-zygotic transition", Fly, vol. 16, no. 1, pp. 111–117, Dec. 2022, ISSN: 1933-6934 (Article).
- P. L. Ferree, S. Di Talia, "Developmental Biology: Embryos Need to Control Their Nucleotides Just Right", Current Biology, vol. 29, no. 7, R252–R254, Apr. 2019, ISSN: 09609822 (Preview).
- P. L. Ferree, S. Di Talia, "Chemical Waves in Embryonic Cell Cycles", *Israel Journal of Chemistry*, vol. 58, no. 6, pp. 714–721, 2018, ISSN: 18695868 (Review).
- P. L. Ferree, S. Di Talia, "For Embryos, Mother Can Only Take You So Far", *Developmental Cell*, vol. 42, no. 3, pp. 203–205, 2017, ISSN: 18781551 (Preview).
- P. L. Ferree, V. Deneke, S. Di Talia, "Measuring time during early embryonic development", Seminars in Cell and Developmental Biology, 2016, ISSN: 10849521 (Review).
- L. M. Carcoba, J. E. Orfila, L. E. Natividad, O. V. Torres, J. A. Pipkin, **P. L. Ferree**, E. Castañeda, D. E. Moss, L. E. O'Dell, "Cholinergic transmission during nicotine withdrawal is influenced by age and pre-exposure to nicotine: Implications for teenage smoking", *Developmental Neuroscience*, vol. 36, no. 3-4, pp. 347–355, 2014, ISSN: 14219859 (Article).
- O. V. Torres, J. A. Pipkin, **P. L. Ferree**, L. M. Carcoba, L. E. O'Dell, "Nicotine withdrawal increases stress-associated genes in the nucleus accumbens of female rats in a hormone-dependent manner", *Nicotine and Tobacco Research*, vol. 17, no. 4, pp. 422–430, 2014, ISSN: 1469994X (**Article**).

## Manuscripts in Progress

- P. L. Ferree, C. Ribalta, A. CØ Jensen, A. Brostrøm, T. Berthing, K. A. Jensen, "Airborne nano/microplastics in the plastics recycling and manufacturing industry" (Article In Preparation).
- P. L. Ferree, S. Brantley, T. Starr, A. Chao, S. Di Talia, "Activator-accumulation and repressor-depletion time mitosis during *Drosophila* gastrulation" (Article In Preparation).

## Select Talks and Poster Presentations

- P. L. Ferree, "Technical and epistemic objects in cell-type classification: A study of single-cell sequencing", Society for Philosophy of Science in Practice (SPSP), Columbia, SC, USA, May 2024 (Poster).
- P. L. Ferree, C. Ribalta, A. Jensen, J. K. Nøjgaard, S. Nielsen, N. Sahlgren, T. Berthing, K. A. Jensen, "Workplace exposure to ultrafine particles, chemicals, and dust during plastic production with recycled plastics", British Occupational Hygiene Society: Inhaled Particles and NanOEH, Manchester, UK, May 2023 (Talk).
- P. L. Ferree, A. De Simone, S. Di Talia, "An activator-repressor model for improved temporal precision of transcription", Quantitative Biology (Q-Bio), Oahu, HI, USA, Feb 2019 (Talk).
- P. L. Ferree, C. Bunce, "The Questions of Developmental Biology", The Society for Developmental Biology (SDB), Boston, MA, USA, Jul 2019 (Poster).
- P. L. Ferree, A. De Simone, S. Di Talia, "An activator-repressor model for improved temporal precision of transcription", Tissue Self-Organization: Challenging the Systems, Heidelberg, Germany, Mar 2018 (Poster).

## SELECT SCHOOLS AND WORKSHOPS ATTENDED AS A STUDENT

European Advanced School for the Philosophy of the Life Sciences, Konrad Lorenz Institute, Austria, Sep 2024.

Summer School on the History of Knowledge, Lund University (LUCK), Sweden, Aug 2024.

Crossing the Disciplinary Boundaries of Physics, Bohr Centennial, Copenhagen, Denmark, Aug 2023.

Workshop on Methods in the Philosophy of Science, University of Vienna, Austria, May 2023.

Summer School on the History of the Life Sciences, Ischia, Italy, Jun 2022.

Winter School on Quantitative Biology, International Center for Theoretical Physics, Trieste, Italy, Dec 2017.

## ACADEMIC SOCIETIES

Member, International Society for the History, Philosophy, and Social Studies of Biology, 2024-present.

Member, Society for Philosophy of Science in Practice, 2023-present.

Member, Philosophy of Science Association, 2024-present.

Member, History of Science Society, 2024-present.

Member, The Richard Rorty Society, 2019-present.

## SERVICE TO THE COMMUNITY

Member of Editorial Team, Society for Philosophy of Science in Practice Newsletter, 2024-present.

## REFERENCES

#### Karin Tybjerg, PhD

Associate Professor, Medical Museion and CBMR, University of Copenhagen

Email: karin.tybjerg@sund.ku.dk, Phone:  $+45\ 35\ 32\ 38\ 03$ 

#### Sara Green, PhD

Associate Professor, History and Philosophy of Science, University of Copenhagen

Email: sara.green@ind.ku.dk, Phone: +45 35 33 46 32

#### Keld Alstrup Jensen, PhD

Professor, Chemistry and Microbiology, National Research Centre for the Working Environment

Email: kaj@nfa.dk, Phone: +45 20 76 47 31

#### Stefano Di Talia, PhD

Associate Professor, Department of Cell Biology, Duke University

Email: stefano.ditalia@duke.edu, Phone: +1 919 684 8079